Guide to the Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records, 1970-1998.
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records
- Series VII. Architectural Projects, Commissions, and Built Works, 1964-1998 (SOM Years)
  - Chemical Bank - Hospital for Special Surgery projects
    - Commercial Bank of Kuwait, Ahmad Al-Jaber II Operations Center, Kuwait City, Kuwait, 1979-1984
      - Technical documents: SOM File index number / Description
        - 2021/320 Reports (testing and field), Undated (Box 12, Folder 27-31)
        - 2021/320 Reports (testing and field), Undated (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
        - 2021/322 Job status reports, Undated (Box 13, Folder 5-15)
        - 2021/330 Personnel, Undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
        - 2021/340 Approval letters, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
        - 2021/350 Change orders, Undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
        - 2021/351 Change estimates, Undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
        - 2021/352 Change orders, Undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
        - 2021/353 Bulletin changes, Undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
        - 2021/354 Field order changes, Undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
        - 2021/360 Requisitions and payments, Undated (Box 13, Folder 23-24)
        - 2021/361 Payments, Undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
        - 2021/370 Permits, Undated (Box 13, Folder 26)
        - 2021/380 Glass block, finish hardware, etc., Undated (Box 13, Folder 27)
        - 2021/381 Bids and proposals, Undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
        - 2021/382 Bids and proposals, Undated (Box 13, Folder 29)
        - 2021/389 Partitions and furniture, Undated (Box 13, Folder 30)
        - 2021/400 Furniture and furnishings, RFP, volumes 1-2, October 31, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
        - 2021/400 Furniture and furnishings, pre qualifications from accepted bidders, February 22, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 11-17)
        - 2021/400 Furniture and furnishings, pre qualifications from rejected bidders, February 22, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 18-30)
    - Deering Milliken Research Center, Spartanburg, South Carolina, 1958
      Beginning of campus 1958
      Corporate headquarters and research center for a textile manufacturing corporation and continuing services.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 41, Folder 23)
      - Photocopies (oversized) of photographs of plan, exteriors, interiors, and Roger Milliken, Undated (Box 33)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Published articles, Undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Dela Rosa Tower, Manila, Philippines, c. 1995-1996
      A project for MegaWorld Properties and Holdings, the Dela Rosa Tower was designed to include retail, recreational, and office space.
      - Design Drawings (Box 75, 76)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 41, Folder 24)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Prospectus, including photographs of model, floor plans, elevators, sections, and schematics; personnel list, Undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Dulles International Airport, Main Terminal Expansion, Chantilly, Virginia, 1989-1997
      Review and update of 1985 master plan (1990)
      Marilyn J. Taylor, planning partner.
      Two-level extension of Main Terminal to accommodate international arrivals; and expansion and renovation of the landmarked Main Terminal Building, designed by Eero Saarinen in the late 1950s (1997), and Midfield Concourse (1997)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 41, Folder 25)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project summary and published articles, Undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Euro Asia Centre, Beijing, China, 1994-1995
      Originally called Beijing Mixed Use II. Includes retail center, office towers, residential buildings, and parking for 1100 cars
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project summary and awards application, Undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Prospectus including reduced copies of drawings and cost estimates, Undated (Box 33)
    - Euro Asia City, Beijing, China, 1994-1995
      Originally called Beijing Mixed Use II. Includes retail center, office towers, residential buildings, and parking for 700 cars.
      - Design Drawings, Undated (Box 59, 72, 87)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project summary and awards application, Undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Prospectus including reduced copies of drawings and cost estimates, Undated (Box 33)
    - Forte Grande, Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates, 1996
      Project only. Was to adjoin the preexisting Forte Grand [sic] Hotel.
      - Publicity brochure, Undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - General Electric Company Corporate Headquarters, Fairfield, Connecticut, 1974
      Ray O. Allen, design partner
      Michael A. McCarthy, senior designer
      1986-1988 Courtyard and podium restored
      1981-1982 Physical fitness facility
      1981-1983 Corporate guest facility,
      SOM Project #1210
      The GE Corporate Headquarters includes two three-story buildings constructed around landscaped interior courts. The Physical Fitness Facility is located in the original headquarters complex, and includes exercise, aerobic, track, and medical facilities, lockers, a lounge, and administrative offices. The Guesthouse is a four-level facility located west of the preexisting headquarters complex, and comprises 26 guest rooms and a conference center with meeting rooms and dining facilities.
      - Working drawings (Headquarters and Guest Facility) (Box 77a, 77b, 78, 79, 80)
      - Photographs (Headquarters), Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides (Fitness Facility and Guest Facility), Undated (Box 49)
      - Design guidelines and project criteria (Guest Facility), Undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Landscaping proposals (Headquarters), Undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - About the Art in the General Electric Conference Center and Guest House., Undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Project summaries, awards application, and published articles., Undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - SOM Lectures, Undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - General Electric Lighting Institute, Nela Park, Cleveland, Ohio, 1987
      - Published materials on Nela Park, Undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - SOM project proposal, Undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - General Motors Corporation, 767 Fifth Avenue, New York, 1994-1995
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Videotape, Undated (Box 30)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project fact sheet, Undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Georgia Pacific Center, Atlanta, Georgia, 1978-1982
      The Georgia-pacific Center is a 52-story regional headquarters office facility with a 700-car garage. Louise Nevelson's environmental sculpture Dawn's Forest adorns the lobby
      - Drawings/Plans (Box 81)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - AIA Atlanta Chapter presentation, Undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Georgia-Pacific Art Program, project fact sheet, project summary, awards applications, Undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Advertising brochures, Published articles, Undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - SOM Lectures, Undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Goldman, Sachs Computer Facility, (New York Computer Center II) Staten Island, New York, 1986
      Located on the five-acre site of the Teleport project on Staten Island, the Goldman Sachs Computer Facility is a two-story building consisting of an office wing, a computer module, and separate mechanical and electrical services.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project summary and awards application, Undated (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Greenville-Spartanburg Airport, Greer, South Carolina, 1959–1962
      1962–1990 Continuing services
      SOM Project #1215 and #1274
      1985-1989 Master plan for expansion of total airport facilities, planned to the year 2006, includes complete functional reorganization, architectural and interior design of airport terminal building, bridges, passenger concourses, fire and crash building, control tower and parking garage, and support facilities. Continuing services include phased expansion study and interior architecture of ticketing, lounge, restaurant, and baggage claim areas
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Project summaries and awards applications., Undated (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Souvenir program for opening of expanded facilities includes time line of airport development, Undated (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Artwork for terminal, restaurant, and other areas, Undated (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Harlem USA, New York, 1993-1997
      - Elevation (Box 72)
      - Design drawings, Undated (Mapcase-folder 9)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Photocopies of design drawings, published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 26, Folder 14)
      - Advertisements, Undated (Box 33)
    - Harvard Square Rapid Transit Station, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1979–1982
      Urban design, architecture, graphics design and streetscape renovations for a subway station.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project summary, awards application, and published articles, Undated (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Herrera Street / Makati Center, Manila, Philippines, 1995
      - Prospectus, including summary, photographs, and reduced copies of drawings, Undated (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Hospital for Special Surgery, New York, 1994-1996
      Interior design.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 42)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 49)
      - Project summary and fact sheet (by Architecture for Health, Science & Commerce P.C.), Undated (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Invitations to groundbreaking and opening ceremonies, Undated (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - IBM Corporate Headquarters - Lever House
    - IBM Corporate Headquarters, King Street, Armonk, New York, 1963
      1975-1978 Renovation of corporate headquarters facility including new lighting, finish materials, and executive suite.
      1977 Study for a new headquarters facility and addition to existing headquarters facility.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 41)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - IBM Customer Service Center Prototype Armonk, New York, 1981
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
    - Islamic Cultural Center of New York, East 96th-97th Streets and Third Avenue New York, New York, 1986 - 1991
      SOM Project #6081
      The Islamic Cultural Center of New York comprises a 1,000-person mosque, an assembly room, and minaret (the latter designed by the architectural firm of Swanke Hayden Connell). It was the first religious center built for New York’s Muslim community and, with its minaret and copper-clad, precast dome, creates a striking presence in its Upper East Side community. The building is rotated on its site to face Mecca, breaking out of the city street grid. SOM’s original master plan also called for an administrative building containing classrooms, a library, offices, a conference hall, an apartment for the Imam, and a 20-car parking garage(unbuilt).
      - Drawings - Design for dome base circumference, by Manuel Keene, comprising verses from the Qur’an (II: 255–257) in a modern computer adaptation of Kufic calligraphy, and sign band for the entrance of Gate-house (see also Shop drawing 04425 36-1), August 4th, 1989 (Box 36)
      - Preliminary design work and details, including sketches, drawings, proposals, and specifications for the dome, mimbar, shoe cabinet, finials, doors, windows, stairs, fencing, cabinetwork, lighting, flooring, and carpeting; working drawings (Box 83)
      - Preliminary design work and details, including sketches, drawings, proposals, and specifications for the dome, mimbar, shoe cabinet, finials, doors, windows, stairs, fencing, cabinetwork, lighting, flooring, and carpeting; working drawings, Undated (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - Preliminary design work and details, including sketches, drawings, proposals, and specifications for the dome, mimbar, shoe cabinet, finials, doors, windows, stairs, fencing, cabinetwork, lighting, flooring, and carpeting; working drawings, Undated (Mapcase-folder 2)
      - Shop Drawings: SOM Shop drawing file number, Undated
        - 6081/02200 - 04200 (Box 18, Folder 24-27)
        - 6081/04220 - 04425 (Box 19, Folder 1-15)
        - 05120-05700 (Box 20, Folder 1-18)
        - 05700 (Box 21, Folder 1-13)
        - 05700 (Box 22, Folder 1-15)
        - 05700-08815 (Box 23, Folder 1-22)
        - 08815-16400 (Box 24, Folder 1-13)
      - Technical documents: Calculation and Correspondence (not identified by SOM file index numbers), Undated
        - Structural steel inspection reports (Box 14, Folder 31-32)
        - Concrete test reports (Box 14, Folder 33-36)
        - F/T cycle test reports (Box 15, Folder 1)
        - Geographical investigations (including rock contour plan) (Box 15, Folder 2)
        - Engineering calculations (Box 15, Folder 3- 6)
        - Structural drawings (Box 15, Folder 7)
        - Analysis mode shape report (Box 15, Folder 8)
        - Shop drawing and sample transmittal log (Box 15, Folder 9)
        - Wind analysis, dome (5 1/4" floppy disk) (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - SOM File index number / Description, Undated
        - 6081/100 Project administration (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
        - 6081/110 Publicity and promotion (Box 15, Folder 13)
        - 6081/130 Job progress (Box 15, Folder 14)
        - 6081/131 Schedules (Box 15, Folder 15-18)
        - 6081/132 Construction photographs and related correspondence (Box 15, Folder 19-20)
        - 6081/133 Meeting minutes (Box 15, Folder 21-28)
        - 6081/134 Field reports and punch lists (Box 15, Folder 29-30)
        - 6081/135 Transmittals (Box 15, Folder 31-34)
        - 6081/140 Cost estimates (Box 15, Folder 35)
        - 6081/141 Cost estimates (Box 16, Folder 1)
        - 6081/142 Budget reports (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - 6081/150 Codes and permits (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - 6081/153 Codes and permits, zoning (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - 6081/154 Codes and permits, certificate of occupancy (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - 6081/155 Approvals, fire protection (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - 6081/156 Approvals, builders pavement plan (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - 6081/160 Pre-construction, general, including notes for layout of the mosque perimeter inscription (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - 6081/166 Codes and permits, carpet fire retardant (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - 6081/170 Construtruction, general (Box 16, Folder 5-10)
        - 6081/171 Bids and proposals (Box 16, Folder 11-13)
        - 6081/172 Approval Letters (Box 16, Folder 14)
        - 6081/173 Bulletin changes (Box 16, Folder 15)
        - 6081/174 Change estimates (Box 16, Folder 16-18)
        - 6081/175 Change estimates (Box 16, Folder 19)
        - 6081/177 Requisitions and payments (Box 16, Folder 20-31)
        - Requisitions and `payments (Box 17, Folder 1-30)
        - 6081 /177 Requisitions and payments (Box 18, Folder 1-16)
        - 6081/178 Field information (Box 18, Folder 17)
        - 6081/179 Punch lists (Box 18, Folder 17)
        - 6081/192 Shop drawing transmittals (Box 18, Folder 17)
        - 6081/200 Site work (Box 18, Folder 18)
        - 6081/210 Site survey and mapping (Box 18, Folder 18)
        - 6081/220 Subsurface investigations (Box 18, Folder 18)
        - 6081/230 Excavation and foundation (Box 18, Folder 19)
        - 6081/240 Builders pavement plan (Box 18, Folder 19)
        - 6081/250 Catch Basin modifications (Box 18, Folder 19)
        - 6081/260 Transmittals, landscaping (Box 18, Folder 19)
        - 6081/300 Correspondence with contractors (Box 18, Folder 20)
        - 6081/330 Testing and inspections (Box 18, Folder 20)
        - 6081/400 Masonry (Box 18, Folder 20)
        - 6081/500 Metals (Box 18, Folder 20)
        - 6081/510 Structural steel decking (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/580 Testing and inspections, firestopping (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/610 Assembly and installation instructions for mimbar, benches, and shoe cabinets (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/700 Environmental protection (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/800 Doors, windows and glass (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/830 Exit devices (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/900 Finishes (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/920 Carpet (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/950 Paint (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - 6081/1000 Design for Gatehouse panel (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - 6081/1100 Video systems (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - 6081/1200 Furnishings (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - 6081/1500 HVAC (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - 6081/1600 Electrical (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - 6081/1610 Light fixtures (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - 6081/1700 Control systems (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/2000 Sketch drawing SKA-113 (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/5000 Wheel load testing (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/5700 Doors (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/7810 Skylights (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/8800 Fire command station (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/9000 Paint and carpet samples (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/9150 Paint samples (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/15600 Site visit reports (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - 6081/16000 Light fixtures (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - Photographs (also see construction photographs in box 15, folders 15-18) (Box 42)
      - Slides (Box 50)
      - Project summary, awards applications, correspondence, samples (carpet, tile, etc.), job directory, published articles, and newspaper clippings (Box 26, Folder 19-24)
      - Islamic Cultural Center memorabilia (Box 38)
      - 14th Annual Interiors Award, Best in Institutional Design (Box 31)
      - Correspondence, cost estimates, fee analysis, brochure, published articles (oversized) (Box 36)
      - Correspondence, articles, 2002 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - J.P. Morgan Corporate Education Facility New York, 1995
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
    - Joint Banking Center (Bank of Kuwait in the Middle East; Industrial Bank of Kuwait; Kuwait Real Estate Bank) Kuwait City, Kuwait, 1980-1984
      Whitson Overcash, design partner (Competition)
      Interior design for the three 18-story headquarters office towers and interiors for Bank of Kuwait in the Middle East, Industrial Bank of Kuwait, and Kuwait Real Estate Bank.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Project summary, fact sheet, correspondence, photographs of marble samples, awards application, and published articles., Undated (Box 26, Folder 25)
      - For general descriptive material on Kuwait, see Commercial Bank of Kuwait.
    - Kuwait Chancery (Embassy of the State of Kuwait), International Center, Washington, DC, 1978-1982
      SOM Project #2035
      Architectural, engineering, and interior design services for five-story building (two stories below grade), including offices, reception hall with sky-lit atrium, and parking
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Awards application and published articles, Undated (Box 26, Folder 27)
      - Drawings - Presentation drawings, framed Technical documents, Window wall and Stair details Interiors Project (Not identified by SOM File Index numbers) (Box 72, 84a, 84b)
      - Presentation drawings (Mapcase-item Framed)
      - Furniture and furnishings, Undated (Box 24, Folder 14-17)
      - Furniture and furnishings, Undated (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
      - Other technical documents and correspondence, Undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - Plants and planters, internal planting, Undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Kuwait Markets Group, Ahmad Al-Jaber Street Commercial Complex, Kuwait City, Kuwait, 1982
      Design included a three-story retail space and indoor atrium with gardens, pools, and fountains.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Project note, reduced copies of drawings, functional program analysis, and fact sheet., Undated (Box 26, Folder 28)
      - For general descriptive material on Kuwait, see Commercial Bank of Kuwait.
    - Kuwait Markets Group, Al-Hilalli Street Commercial Complex, Kuwait City, Kuwait, 1982
      The design is semicircular in shape, including atrium and glass roof.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Project notes and fact sheet., Undated (Box 26, Folder 28)
      - For general descriptive material on Kuwait, see Commercial Bank of Kuwait.
    - Kuwait Waterfront, Phase V Salmiya District, Kuwait City, Kuwait, 1996
      Phase V was divided into three different but related environments: the Commercial Center, the Waterfront District, and the Beach Front/Promenade.
      - Design drawings (Box 85)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Videotapes, Undated (Box 30)
      - Correspondence, drawings list., Undated (Box 26, Folder 29)
      - For general descriptive material on Kuwait, see Commercial Bank of Kuwait.
    - Lehrer McGovern Bovis, New York, New York, 1992-1993
      Interior architecture for corporate headquarters including executive, private, and open offices, private and employee dining, kitchen, and boardroom.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Project summary, awards application, and published articles, Undated (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - Lenox Hill Hospital, New York, 1987–1997
      1989 Master plan and programming for expansion and modernization of teaching hospital
      1990–1995 Planning and design for proposed addition and renovation, relocation, and expansion of existing facilities
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 43)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Project summaries and personnel list, Undated (Box 26, Folder 31)
    - Lever House, New York, 1951
      1984-1986 Plaza renovations
      This project involved repaving the plaza of one of SOM’s most significant designs of the 1950s.
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
  - Mangaf Resort Hotel - Presbyterian Hospital of New York
    - Mangaf Resort Hotel Kuwait City, Kuwait, 1996-1997
      Master plan and architecture of waterfront resort with luxury and business class hotels, residential villas, marina, recreational, and retail facilities.
      - Sketches (Box 86)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Videotape, Undated (Box 30)
    - McKinsey & Company, 245 Park Avenue, New York
      Interior architecture for headquarters office.
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - RFP, alternate locations study, and correspondence., Undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - MegaWorld Centre, Manila, Philippines, 1992-1997
    - MegaWorld Place, Manila, Philippines, 1996-1997
      A mixed-used structure including offices, a hotel, residential space, and parking. Two versions of this project were prepared for the client. The second scheme represents a complete rethinking of the design based on the constraint that the client was unable to obtain the land needed to build the first scheme. Consequently, the entire program was consolidated into one building instead of two.
      - Design drawings, Plans, Elevations, Elevator details (Box 72, 87)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - SOM Metro Manila project listing, personnel list, correspondence, published articles, and other promotional material, including information of general interest on the Makati District of Manila and the Philippines, Undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Methodist Hospital Medical Pavilion, Brooklyn, New York, 1992–1997
      SOM Project #90264
      1992 Schematic design and planning for elder-care facility with 260-bed long-term care home, physicians’ offices, retail, adult day care center, and below-grade parking
      1994 Architecture and interior architecture for a five-story mixed-use medical office building, including physicians’ offices, retail, and below-grade parking
      - Reduced copies of working drawings (Box 88)